{
  "sourceFile": "2021-International-Geography-Bee-Regional-Finals-Set-1-Round-2.txt",
  "count": 10,
  "items": [
    {
      "qno": 1,
      "question": "This country includes the limestone coral island of Caye Caulker. This country's Cayo Region is home to the ancient Mayan ruins at Xunantunich [[shoo-nahn-TOO-nitch]]. This country's natural attractions include a giant marine sinkhole called the Great Blue Hole. This is the only country in Central America whose official language is English. For the point, name this country formerly known as British Honduras, whose capital is Belmopan.",
      "answer": "Belize"
    },
    {
      "qno": 2,
      "question": "The Thunder Dragon Druk is depicted on this country's national flag. This country is home to the cliffside Tiger's Nest monastery. This country also is home to Gangkhar Puensum, the tallest unclimbed mountain in the world. This country, whose national language is Dzongkha, is ruled by the Wangchuck dynasty. For the point, name this small Himalayan monarchy whose capital is Thimphu",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Bhutan"
    },
    {
      "qno": 3,
      "question": "Major cities on this island include Kupang and Baucau. This island, the largest of the Outer Banda Islands, has its highest point at Ramelau. The exclave of Oecusse [[WEH- CYUSE]] lies on the western part of this island. The eastern half of this island was colonized by Portugal following the establishment of the capital city of Dili. For the point, name this Southeast Asian island split between Indonesia and a namesake country.",
      "answer": "Timor"
    },
    {
      "qno": 4,
      "question": "One feature with this name is home to the Deux Mamelles, a pair of volcanoes whose name means \"two treats.\" A country with this name is divided into the Barlavento and Sotavento Islands. That country of this name also includes the island of Pogo. The westernmost point on continental Africa has this name. For the point, give this name shared by a peninsula in Senegal and an island country whose capital is Praia.",
      "answer": "Republic of Cape Verde"
    },
    {
      "qno": 5,
      "question": "The shores of this body of water were formerly the site of the cities of Nguimi [[NGWEE-mee]] and Bol. One proposal to restore this body of water was the Transqua Project, which would have redirected water from the Ubangi River. This Sahel lake has lost over 95% of its historic volume. For the point, name this rapidly drying-up African lake which shares its name with a country governed from N'Djamena [[un-jah-MAY-nah]].",
      "answer": "Lake Chad 2020-21 Geography Bee One Geography Bee One - Round 2"
    },
    {
      "qno": 6,
      "question": "According to local legend, these objects were transported to their current location by being \"walked.\" By the mid-1800s, the only examples of these objects to have not been toppled were at Rano Raraku. Many of these objects were originally topped with a pukao, a red hat-like object which may have represented a chieftain's topknot. For the point, name these head-shaped monoliths created by the Rapa Nui people of Easter Island.",
      "answer": "Mo'ai"
    },
    {
      "qno": 7,
      "question": "The city of Kuching is on this island and serves as the capital of the Sarawak State. This island's northern tip consists of the Sabah State, and the city of Bandar Seri Begawan is the capital of a sultanate located entirely on this island. For the point, name this third largest island in the world, which is divided between Malaysia, Indonesia, and Brunei.",
      "answer": "Borneo"
    },
    {
      "qno": 8,
      "question": "Near the town of Sankt Gore, this river wraps around the Lorelei Rock. This river flows through Lake Constance, where it forms an inland delta. This river originates in Lake Tomasee in Switzerland and discharges in the Netherlands. Major cities along this river include Cologne and Dusseldorf. For the point, name this European river which forms the border between France and Germany.",
      "answer": "Rhine River"
    },
    {
      "qno": 9,
      "question": "This state is sometimes known as the Battle Born State for achieving statehood during the U.S. Civil War. An annual festival featuring the burning of a wooden effigy is hosted at a temporary city in this state's Black Rock Desert. This state's largest city is served by McCarran International Airport and is home to many casinos, including the Venetian and Caesars Palace. For the point, name this western U.S. state whose capital is Carson City.",
      "answer": "Nevada"
    },
    {
      "qno": 10,
      "question": "The building of one of these structures on the uninhabited island of MÃ¤rket led to a territorial dispute between Finland and Sweden. The tallest brick example of these structures in the United States is located at Cape Hatteras. One of these structures in ancient Alexandria was known as the Pharos. For the point, name these towers which shine out to sea in order to prevent shipwrecks.",
      "answer": "lighthouses"
    }
  ]
}